soft & jeering radio episode 133
continuous integration with Chris Reed
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at s II - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
support
[Music]
welcome listeners to a new episode of
software engineering radio recall it at
yahoo 2008 so this time we're going to
talk about a topic that has been
requested a couple of times sometimes
people accuse us of discussing all kinds
of advanced fancy stuff but not looking
at the basic hands-on stuff people need
to know to actually run projects and one
of those topics that we didn't cover
here that falls in that category is
continuous integration and today we are
going to talk about that with Chris Reed
from thought works hi Chris Hey how you
doing I'm fine I'm tired as we just
discussed yeah but it doesn't matter I
just have to ask questions excellent all
the hard working yeah so Chris please
introduce yourself to our listeners yes
my name is Chris Reid I work for Thor
works have been the works now for almost
four years
I'm there's an infrastructure specialist
so what I do is my background is mostly
system administration I've been a
developer as a developer for a couple of
years but then found that hardware
infrastructure networks and all that
kind of stuff was was what really
interested me more so but now work for
thought works I work kind of helping
developers interact with us with the
settlement teams mm-hm
at the clients and part of that is
actually hinges all around continuous
integration getting continuous
integration I've been working in the
clients and all the automation that that
goes around continuous integration is
kind of the the things that I get
involved with right okay so so most
people probably have heard about
continuous integration so why don't you
give us a little bit of an let's say
overview why this is important and what
it is so continuous integration is is
all about ensuring that you've got
better quality code it's it's processes
that that have come about to help you
improve the quality and the confidence
that you have in the code that comes out
at the end of the line so the whole idea
is that you know you know 10-15 years
ago when people were developing code
particularly you know
big enterprise bits of code what they'd
find is they would find that you know as
as they're going through you would have
Bob developing on one side and he'd have
his own branch and he'd be running a
coding and he had a thread running along
doing some others and and once they
they've completed their code trying to
get their code to work together and one
program was was a big problem and also
you know once the code was finished in
inverted commas there would often be
lots of bugs lots of problems and lots
of issues trying to get it into
production
so continuous integrations a set of
practices that you can put into place to
help you catch the bugs early to help
you get rid of this merge hell and and
you know just just also help teams be
more efficient to help them
concentrating on getting code getting
functionality out there because it
doesn't matter how beautiful your code
is doesn't matter how wonderful the
languages that you're developing in
particularly in the enterprise space if
it's not running in production somewhere
and making someone money it's absolutely
useless yeah absolutely yeah yeah the
best that you could say it's a kind of
intermediate step towards that goal of
running somewhere and but the edge' list
of course will say no everything needs
to run every time all the time forever
so so we covered the why how do you do
this what's the let's say 10,000 foot
overview over continuous integration so
the key things that that key themes the
kind of crop up in in all these these
little practices that you can do is is
first around fast feedback you know
letting the developers see very quickly
if what he's doing is the correct thing
and if it's working and and if it's
doing what he expects it to do in the
context of the rest of the system the
other key thing that comes up is
repeatability being able to repeatably
do it over and over again repeatably
test over and over again that again what
you think you're writing is actually
what's supposed to be there and the
other thing that's kind of a nice side
effect which which you know as people
who carry on about agile going about is
is it encourages collective code
ownership if you've got Bob working on a
module over here and Fred working on a
module over there
you know they become very possessive of
their code they're protective of their
code and and that's a real problem that
causes lots of social problems within
the development organization yeah and so
by doing these practices and encourages
collective ownership instead of being
proud and protective of your module you
can start being proud of the whole
application you're developing yeah so
this is an interesting point because it
probably requires that the
organizational structure the team
structure the project structure the
process takes this into account and it's
kind of adapted towards being able to
have those properties you just talked
about yeah that's correct so there's a
process aspect in addition to a tool and
practices aspect yes correct it's not
just you can't just drop in some tools
and it'll make everything better you
can't just drop in some practices and
it'll make it everything's better it's
it's it's something that's Gatti that
impacts the whole ecosystem of software
development so let's look at some of the
practices yeah so these core practices
are the core practices that were
outlined by martin fowler and matt
ephemeral in their original paper on
continuous integration and they still
apply today very much their core
practices being having single source
code repository automating your build
automating your testing and publishing
the latest version of the distributable
the latest good build so that people can
actually get hold of it the testers can
get hold of it and play with it and also
so that you can actually get this build
and put it into production right so
let's look at each of those practices I
guess and we'll start with a single
source repository yeah so single source
repository is all about having a single
point of truth a single place where
you've got all the source code that
makes up your application ten years ago
they weren't there wasn't much in the
way of source code management tools and
things like that and I was working on
projects when I was a developer 10 years
ago you know I I was working on code on
my machine and and and my partner was
working on code in his machine and
whenever we wanted to share code or copy
onto disk and cut move it to the other
machine and you know that's very
inefficient and very soon you start to
wonder which disks got the latest
version of the code you know yeah
where's that byte fix that I had you
know and it gets lost and so so it's
it's all about having a central place
nowadays that sort
code management tools are more pervasive
in there they're all over the place
people store often in big companies that
I go to and speak to they have they
still have this my machine mentality all
the developers are working in their own
branch and working on their own code and
it's only every couple of weeks Oh every
couple months that they'll actually
merge these branches together and
they'll have huge problems you know
getting all this code working together
yeah so one of the key things about
having a single source repository is
these days I'll get into later and how
language has changed but these days it's
not just having them in the same
subversion repository or the same
perforce repository or something like
that but actually all working on the
same main line of the code all working
together so that there's a single source
of truth where you get the code there
are still a use for branching but it's
not per developer it's rather per let's
say about an hour customer specific
adaptation of the overall sauce tree or
something
yes correct branching is you know
branching is not totally evil it still
has its value but yet just not having a
branch per developer where each
developer is by themselves writing their
own code I guess it shows that I'm not
that old yet because I don't actually
remember those days I okay before we
move on to the next one them do you have
any specific recommendations about which
repositories are especially useful in
there let's say agile environment and
for this kind of approach yeah
definitely I'm there's one thing we'll
get into tools a bit later but okay the
key thing about any of these tools is
make sure you choose a tool that fits
with your process right okay then let's
cover that later if yeah okay so next
one is automate the built yeah so so you
know one of the key tag lines that I
really like is that using an IDE is not
automating your build why is that and
because the whole thing about automation
is you want it to be repeatable you want
to be able to get exactly the same thing
at exactly the same time when you've got
lots of developers working on a team
working on a project every developer has
their own settings that they put in the
IDE their own little bits and pieces and
generally every IDE on every developer
machine is different yeah okay and and
so again the key is about repeatability
if you've got to drop a code drop in in
production yeah and you know two weeks
after has gone into production you find
a bug you want to be able to go and
see exactly how that source code was but
not only that if you need to fix a bug
if you need to reproduce a bug if you
need to test that the bug has been fixed
you need to rebuild that code exactly as
it was when you built it you know
however long before and IDE settings
change and stuff like that so it's about
getting you know using one of the many
build tools that are out there to to
create a system that will automatically
build its now yeah and I guess one thing
that that that's kind of interesting is
that the configuration or let's say
programming of the build script is
something that is you know by many
developers it's seen as like the
secondary kind of thing as just the
build script but I guess it's a good
idea to - at least conceptually look at
the build script or the build
infrastructure as yet another
development well as a as a first-class
citizen in the development environment
yeah and you know give it the necessary
respect and treatment definitely that's
probably my my biggest battle that I
have a suspect it's it's something I've
been chatting here at jar with Andy
Glover about as well because it's it's
something that that really needs to be
sorted out in a lot of development teams
yes just you know it's the ugly
stepchild of software development you
know it's it's it's part of your code
it's part of what it makes your code
valuable yeah and I guess the the build
automation obviously it doesn't just do
the actual compilation there's also
about deployment units packaging testing
and that's yes yeah we'll get into that
later yes all about making it all
repeatable yeah and also part of that is
is by having it on a build script and
and automating the build it it kind of
helps to be able to reproduce the bill
right and so it's no longer the case of
it works on my machine why doesn't it
work and in the test environments why
doesn't it work in in area by having it
built on a separate environment and part
of a continuous integration process
you're ensuring that you know this but
it works on my machine doesn't crop up
and there's not a valid excuse anymore
yeah yeah and that there is the single
truth right yes that's correct
yeah automating testing is the next
important ingredient I guess yep that's
right and again it's not just about
automating your unit test file it's
about automating all the testing around
your software yeah so again you know
eight years ago when when the paper
first came out you know j-unit was was
new on the scene and everyone was
getting their heads around this unit
testing concept and that's now a problem
that's been pretty well solved there's
lots of alternate tools and stuff like
it and so it's now expanding the horizon
of where you get into the testing it's
it's moving into to integration test
functional test performance tests part
of your continuous integration testing
UI testing acceptance testing in our
high level running right through your
application yeah and then also as part
of automating the testing making sure
that you're actually asserting something
in your tests and then if something is
wrong you fail the build yeah and you
stop and you let people have a look and
and and get into it often I'll go to
clients and they'll say we're doing
continuous integration but we're not
getting any value and you have a look at
what they're doing or what they're doing
is is they may be running a nightly
build and you know four days out of five
it's broken and no one care and and this
is one of the key things when you
automate your testing you know make sure
that your testing is valid and make sure
that when the build breaks when their
tests fail you figure that's the highest
priority it doesn't do anything else
right exactly that's that's that's one
of the key things when the builds broken
when it's red yeah you know can't fix it
yeah
the next one is about publishing the
latest distributable which is of course
closely related to the whole agile idea
and you know making sure that every
incremental release is actually useful
to some extent to some of the
stakeholders at least so I guess that's
what you're getting it here yeah exactly
it's it's it's it's one of the key
things about when when I talk about
continuous integration and when I you
know implemented it different clients is
that you only have one stage where you
actually compile and assemble your
distributable package and that's right
at the beginning you're later automated
tests further down the pipeline
they don't recompile their own version
of the binaries you know one place where
it's compiled and then everyone takes
that distributable and they'll deploy it
into a UAT environment they'll deploy
that binary into performance testing
apparently what u eighty and user
acceptance test ah it's a common term in
the UK and and then also you know into
your performance test environments into
your staging area and also
to production that's the binary that
goes there because this also makes sure
that the actual distributable package
that you're testing that you're actually
running all these tests on is actually
what's in production yeah
and contains all the resources it
actually needs to correct yeah okay
that's that's um well if the first thing
was the 10,000 foot overview I guess now
we read like 3,000 feet yeah
and we can now look at the progress over
time of some of the practices tools
languages that are used here to make
this a little bit more concrete and
hands-on for people instead of just just
talking about you know concept yeah yeah
yeah yeah so this is practice evolution
things things that have come up that
people need to do pretty much all the
time that kind of help continuous
integration be more valuable the first
one is ready to commit more often yeah
you know checking in once a week you
know is a bad thing you need to check in
at least once a day these days I try and
get teams to aim for you know at least
once an hour check-in regularly because
you know what happens is if the build
fails and the bill does fail and that's
not a bad thing that's giving you
information there are more feedback for
you to use the key thing is that if the
bill does fail you know then if you've
you know your last check-in was an hour
ago at worst you've lost an hour's work
if you need to back it up if you need to
rethink about it whereas you know if
you're only checking in in it once a
week you're gonna lose a week's work
potential yeah and and it's again it's
about feedback it's about context it's
about mental state if you've just made a
change now and something breaks chances
are it'll be very obvious to you why it
broke yeah you know and stuff like it
but of course conversely now this is
where we start to get to to the needs of
the rest of the of the ecosystem is that
to do this efficiently developers need
to be given smaller units of work right
but that goes together well with you
know the agile XP scrum storying very
boring kind of thing where you you write
small simple user stories and you break
them down into into steps that
themselves know they might not have to
sense but they're at least testable yes
exactly small testable units
you know the whole test-driven
development thing you write your tests
write your code as soon as it's all good
check it in okay don't go again and one
of the key things also about committing
more often is it is it forces you to
update if you want to clean commit you
need to be updating regulator this
presupposes this kind of work with
subversion CVS where you do a optimistic
merge kind of thing I mean in other
environments it might be different
because you have locked all the stuff
you know so yes correct correct so
generally I find that the the the
pessimistic locking works you know it
has issues where yeah I agree
just to just have the calm yeah yeah
yeah okay so next one is to to to to
make sure that every commit triggers a
build yes that's correct
and again it's all about fast feedback
it's all about you know getting those
small changes and making less to fix and
getting that information going and and
do you really I mean question do you
really want every commit to build or is
it you know good enough or as good to
actually have a built every hour so that
effectively or more or less every
comment kind of results in a builder why
is it important that that commit
actually triggers the build as opposed
to just having real-time building again
it's all about fast feedback it's you
want to know why if you've only got a
builder scheduled every hour then then
basically if you miss that hour window
by five minutes you know you're gonna
have to sit and wait and twiddle your
thumbs and maybe work on something else
you know for fifty five minutes while
you waiting for feedback coming back in
whereas you know I suppose it's it's a
bit it's a bit strange having a look at
every commit builds because and there
may be windows where a build actually
runs two or three commits and so it does
get a bit a bit strange but in other
words when the build is running as you
commit that you don't do anything yeah
yeah correct well until it's finished
intent with it yet yeah but then that
that runs the risk of if if one of the
previous commits breaks the build yeah
you've now got more changes to figure
out it's not just one change set that's
broken it so ideally you want every
commit to build yeah and to do that your
build needs to be fast you need to be
able to get that quickly Rebecca if
you're working on a ten minute
cycle with some of the most productive
teams I've seen they're checking in
every 10 minutes you know your build
needs to give me your feedback within
that 10 minutes like do you do require
or recommend that developers run their
own built locally and then only if that
works they check in and run the the the
real build or is that kind of over half
yeah no I definitely believe that I'm a
big fan of developer discipline to get
continuous integration working properly
you know one of the key things about
that is developer discipline the
developers need to keep themselves
disciplined to not check in on a broken
build to check in as you know frequently
to update frequently to do this and so
there there is probably a bit more more
discipline required on the developers
but part of that for me is developers
running a local build it doesn't have to
be the full build because that could
take you know they may have different
spec machines yeah things like this yeah
but you know just run a set of tests
locally on the development machine
before you know once you've updated and
kind of done a local merge before you
push that back make sure that
everything's working together and then
push it in now cuz you know you'll find
issues probably and then by fixing it
locally you don't impact other teams
who've done that stuff and I've already
got a working locally no the other thing
then is to test in in an environment
that is realistic with regards to the
environment the final product is gonna
run it right oh yes oh yes even up until
recently before you know multi-core
processors became common developers are
generally working on single CPU desktops
and that's where they're doing the
coding and the biggest place we saw this
was was within multi-threaded code
developers would run the test locally on
their single CPU machine and everything
would run fine
yeah as soon as they they check it in
and the continuous integration server
built it on a multiprocessor box and
tested it was multi processors you know
they would then discover issues they
would describe race conditions and all
sorts of issues and again it still
applies today with things like cluster
issues if you you know deploying and
testing even in your continuous
integration environment if you're
deploying and running your functional
tests against a single node server and
your production environments are cluster
yeah you know we've had issues where you
know people don't discover you know
these problems that pop up in clustered
environment and again when you're
testing an
production clone it's not about this
having the same scale the same
throughput the same stuff because
generally that most you'll maybe have
two or three users on the system now
it's just about the architecture getting
the moving parts right although it's of
probably worth mentioning that of course
there are kinds of tests let's say the
classical unit tests that don't
necessarily require the full
infrastructure to be there once you do
integration test with database access
with data replication whatever there's
this the thing we're talking about
becomes more critical yes correct and
this is again where with continuous
integration pipelines come in which is
which is a whole nother subject but
basically yeah it's all about you know
moving it further on testing you know
including with with having the right
database architecture I've been on
projects where to keep the unit tests
fast they've been testing with an
in-memory database yeah but you know the
production has been one of the big
relational databases and then all of a
sudden you know there will be small
semantic changes in the sequel there'll
be you know bugs and either
implementation and hey it works fine in
memory and it runs fast
yeah but trying to get it to run on the
production database has been you know
they had a lot of pain the reason why
people ran it on you know in-memory
databases is of course two things first
of all the the infrastructure might be
expensive yes and the other thing if you
run on a you know big system it might
take a lot of time to set the you know
the test environment up and therefore
it's a problem with getting the rapid
feedback yes so I guess one goal is to
keep the build fast and then how do you
do this this is again we build pipelines
come in in that what's a build pipeline
so I'll probably touch on them briefly
here so this is originally a paper that
Dan North myself and Joe humble did at
agile 2006 and it's it's all about you
know instead of in the old traditional
continuous integration concept you would
have a big build server yeah and you
know that build server would just you
know run something like cruise control
but then you just have a project and
that runs a build and that's it and
that's all you have you know the whole
what we found was was winning at clients
we needed more information we needed the
fast feedback from unit tests but we
would have you know functional
functional tests integration is that
we're taking a long time so what we do
is we would start to chain chain the
builds to
in several stages yes exactly so what
you do is you have a pipeline going into
one end of the pipeline is your source
code coming out the other end is your
production code right and what you do is
the pipeline is made up of stages and
each stage consists of you know multiple
jobs that can be run in parallel so you
know your first stage just as you're
doing your building and your packaging
could also be running in parallel it
could be generating your Java ducts it
could be running your code coverage or
your your static Feinberg's analysis or
something like that and you know and
that would all be part of the first
stage you know running your unit test
and then that would be the the kind of
key checking mechanism but then later on
further down the pipeline once those at
all passed you'll then have another
build that's now deploying it into a
kind of small fast environment and then
running a whole suite of functional
tests does it all work and once you've
done that and you kind of you're
increasing your confidence as you move
along okay that works in that
environment now we get to the resource
intensive stage you know you may be you
know running with a big db2 database
that's 100 or something like that yeah
and and you know then you run the same
things again but on the proper
environment so it moves along further
down the stages now and and you know as
you get further down you get more and
more confidence on the quality of your
code but you're getting the feedback
earlier for your developers to allow
them to track on and and the the hardest
thing about that from a developer
perspective is actually having the
discipline to treat stage just treat
failures further down in later stages
with as much importance as as you're
your own stage that's see there's the
first stage it didn't grow but the key
thing is to make sure that all the
stages kind of all linked to one change
set right so that you know if it does
fail half an hour later in the
production like environment you've got
the change that you can see what's
changed it and normally what that means
is that you've been got a failure that
you need to catch further up and so what
you'll probably do is you'll find a ha
there's a unit test a schematic for it
I'll catch that environment put it in
and you're captured earlier yeah okay so
and again the reason for keeping the
build fast as you just alluded
- is to keep the feedback timely so you
can really relate to the source of the
problem that created the failing test
yes that's exactly it
okay one thing that I actually wrote
down here as a note that wanted to talk
to you about but now we do it anyway is
that of course you need a way to
communicate failures and success and
maybe also metrics performance
measurements back to the developers so
they are actually aware of things yes
so what kind of tools support can you
have to make people aware to make them
see what's actually happening yeah so
these were what I normally referred to
as information radiators you know
something that's just lying around
letting people know you know common
things that I've seen is kind of lava
lamps you know within the project area
space you'll have a red one and a green
one as long as the green lava lamps
going you know it's fine we've done it
with lightsabers we had the one client
we were working out we're in two
buildings but we happen to be on the
same floor was a split team we happened
to be on the same floor on each of the
two buildings and we could see each
other through the windows and what we do
is we'd have lightsabers in the window
and then basically you just be able to
look out the window and you could see
what color the other teams like the
lightsaber was and you would know kind
of where you were so kind of getting
this information and there's common
tools like CC tray and things like that
we could just have it running on your
desktop and you know it'll just pop up
you know little alerts when the build
fails there's there's big monitor
screens that you can run this various
little apps to tap into this kind of
information here and just let everyone
know this is the state of the build
because one of the key things again is
about developers when they want to check
in they need to know is the build green
can I check in if it's red don't check
in because you're gonna potentially make
it work make it make it work exactly you
know and also if you notice it's being
read for a long time you know someone's
having a hard problem you can then go in
there see what the change set is see who
last checked in to make the problem and
and you know for the tech leaves on the
projects and stuff like it may be a
chance for them to walk over to that
developer and say you know hey do you
need help with this problem you know and
again this is the collective ownership
campaign yeah everyone concerned yeah
exactly and again it's not about blame
it's not about you know are you broke
the build for the
10th time today it's you know that could
be you know a further indication of
something else that needs to happen
right to bring it up yeah and in
addition to the the big red green lamp I
guess you might have some kind of web
page that gives you an overview of the
failed tests and some statistics about
you know whatever yeah yeah so there's
there's been a lot of movement lately in
the continuous integration server space
I mean thought works wrote the first
continuous integration server cruise
control which kind of came out at the
same time this was the the the the spike
project that that Martin Fowler and Matt
ephemeral were working on that they
actually first wrote the paper on was
was you know the core code for cruise
control came out of there but these days
you know even a thought works we
realized in you know hey cruise control
came to a certain point but you know
we've now got our own CI commercial
rewrite from scratch CI serve a product
out there there's there's there's
there's loes from from different you
know companies there's commercial ones
there's open source ones and they're all
really good and they're all homing in on
this concept of you know getting this
information feedback they're you know
some of them do really good graphs
they'll start to train stuff over
different builds you'll start tracking
things like you know code coverage
performance test results you know all
this kind of stuff number of unit tests
you know build times and stuff like that
and so you can start getting more
information and so what you can do is
you can start actually setting and kind
of more soft failure conditions one of
the projects that did a couple of years
ago which is one of the first ones that
I got involved with doing this was
running performance tests and up
appearance tests or kind of probably the
only case where I'd say yeah showed you
learn to run overnight you know just
pick the latest green bear for the day
and run them overnight but what we were
doing is we were actually every night we
were setting you know what the current
latency was what the throughput was
stuff like this and what we would do is
we would check and we'd set a deviation
if it's now right more than 10% slower
than it was last night at trend analysis
exactly trend analysis that you know if
the trains are starting to go the wrong
way break the build the build because
you know oh it's only about a day's work
that introduced something that's you
know has a huge impact on performance
yeah no no the eclipse guys are also
doing this and that's very very good
because it yeah it's a way to make
performance degradation measurable as a
criterion for for failing the build yeah
yes very slow automating deployment is
of course the last step in a build
pipeline Union well it's not the last
step it's the but last step we yeah do
the automated deployment and then you
run the final tests any thoughts about
that
oh yes so this is one of my my big ones
that are that I really like that that
I've been pushing hard for and it's and
it's become quite quite accepted
recently is it's the whole concept of
you know the the way I describe this is
one of the very first clients always
that it thought works we got there the
plot go live was was a big deal what
what would happen is there would now and
start you know six o'clock and Saturday
morning really really early and they
would shut down their entire system and
what they would do is they would work
through and hopefully by Sunday
lunchtime they would be able to bring
the system back up again with the new
release of the code and there was huge
amounts of stress huge amounts of panic
huge amounts of management visibility
you know paying close attention to
what's going on because they had this
huge manual process of actually getting
the code into place three months later
you know we worked very closely with the
with the UPS team we brought them in we
sat down with them and and we helped
them kind of write a deployment script
that would actually take the code from
the CI server and actually push it into
production and while we did we started
further up line we started pushing into
the staging in the testing environment
and stuff like this and what happened is
you know within three months what we
were doing is they were doing go lives
on Friday lunchtime with less than a
second downtime and they were doing it
while users run the system now do you
know dropping your deployments in here
yeah so I mean by automating your
deployment and by making your automated
deployment part of your continuous
integration ecosystem is when you're
doing your functional test not only are
you testing your application but you're
testing the mechanism that puts your
application into production yeah and by
getting your operating system your ups
guys involved in the process early they
get confidence in it as well so it's not
only you getting and your project
managers getting confidence in the
quality of your code it's now confidence
from the operation guys that they're not
going to get called it two o'clock in
the morning because something's
exploding here
confidence in the actual deployment
mechanism so that quite happily just run
the script which there guys no more
problems yeah yeah that's that's a very
good recommendation to you know always
to get the ops team involved early are
probably very good recommendations
usually they kind of scream at the end
yeah exactly
okay language evolution remember we're
talking about evolution we talked about
practice evolution and now we look at
the language evolution yep
so built yeah so you know ten years ago
you talked about a build or you're
talking about was you know probably at
best you know compiling and linking your
code
hoooray my code compiles it links with
all the libraries you know that's it
nowadays generally when we refer to a
build we we're not just talking about
those those two stages but we're also
talking about you know running unit
tests running code analysis creating the
final deployment package and even
running the deployment invoking the the
deployment scripts from your from your
build script this is one thing where
some people get confused is you know you
have these build scripting languages
like ant one of the I deal a lot with
that and I quite like ant but you know I
often see developers who try to take
this a bit too far they actually try and
write their deployment mechanism in nth
answer language for for doing building
scripts for compiling homers for
managing dependencies let off like a you
know it's not particularly wonderful at
doing deployment but you know write your
deployment script in something that
makes sense and then just use ant
involve the deployment scripts and use
it because you know the operating system
guys the UPS guys when they're doing
level deployments into production they
you know they don't want to be running
ant they won or a shell script so just
invoking a shell script from you and
everyone's covered everyone's happy yeah
okay
integration yeah so you know again years
ago integration used to mean getting
code from various team members working
together getting their code integrated
together into one product nowadays I'm
often hearing the word integrated
meaning getting various projects working
together getting various modules working
together and also getting our systems
working with our third-party vendor
suspect
and abstain sometimes yeah then again
testing you know testings also evolved
it used to mean you know you know maybe
sitting testing my code in isolation
before I checked it in or you know just
testing that it compiles and generally
you know you would find an attitude of
okay take take this test code you know
I'll take the code it's compiled it
links now it's up to the testers to test
it and you know it's kind of bringing
this responsibility back home and
avoiding the throwing over the wall
problem exactly exactly it's all about
teamwork unless that's again you know
testing is not just unit testing it's
also you know various levels of
acceptance testing integration testing
performance testing is there's loads of
different tests that you know need to
run yeah I guess build an integration
and continuous integration is one of
these things that obviously rely heavily
on tools yes so I guess we we should
take a look at how the tool landscape
evolved over time and what today's state
of the art is I guess so for source
control versioning what's the state of
the out there yes
you know source control systems they
they again even as recently as four
years ago you know loads of companies I
suppose even nowadays are still using
CVS yeah and the thing is you know CVS
all being file based and stuff like that
if if you're running a you're cruise
continuous integration server
you know that's polling the the SCM
looking for changes you know CVS dies
CVS can't handle it yeah where is that
the modern source control systems you
know it can all cope with this load
they're much easier at handling polling
handling you know has something changed
they're getting this information out and
so so so these days you know all the
good ones cuz they can cope with the
load of being pulled and looked for
changes by a CI service so what is so
what do we mean by today's system
obviously there is a CVS's successor
subversion yeah so subversion is great
at this but also you know we starting to
use a lot of mercurial internally at
ThoughtWorks especially with with our
distributed agile with our distributed
teams mercurial is wonderful for that
kind of stuff there's some some teams on
some projects using git particularly for
the Ruby projects they seem to tend to
like it I mean and all these tools kind
of handle
also some of the commercial ones that
we're using in our clients perforce
handles it very nicely you know and so
it's it's it's it's states like that you
know those are the players that that I
think are handling it very nicely so so
what is different in tools like
mercurial and maybe we should do an
episode on that at some point and
looking at those different systems can
you give it a brief overview of what
those systems how are they different
from what subversion does I mean why are
they better maybe or aren't they you
know it's it's all about how you use I'm
a very big fan of choosing the right
tool for the right job and yeah you're
right distributed source control
management systems that's an episode or
in itself there's lots of things you can
do with it but I mean what what the key
difference is is you know with something
like CVS with subversion what you have
is you'll have a central source code
server and everyone checks in and pulls
out from that and that's the central
source of truth whereas with the disk
with the distributed ones you've got an
entire repository copy sitting locally
on your machine oh and then what you're
doing is you know you do local check-ins
local check-ins and as as you work and
then what you do is you know the way we
work with materials will have a central
mercurial server which is our central
source of truth no matter what you're
using you need to have a central one
that's the bottom yeah and then what
happens is will be developing locally
you know making little commits locally
and then we're gonna be happy for the CI
server to pick up our changes or when
we're happy for the rest of the team
pick up our changes we push it to stage
committed in some sense exactly exactly
exactly and that's great for spiking and
stuff like Edison spike it out in a
little branch and I know it doesn't work
or stuff like that yeah so that kind of
really makes a difference but what we
have is crews the our new CI server it's
I'm part of the development team but the
development team split these guys in
Beijing there are some guys in Bangalore
there's me in London there's some guys
in San Francisco and and so I kind of
particularly you know in some of the the
lesser developed countries you know
bandwidth is a problem it's not enough
bandwidth the line goes down stuff like
at and so just being able to have to do
the commits locally to do the tests
locally and stuff like that and there
when the link comes up yeah
hey hey there we go okay the other thing
is then of course all the kind of static
analysis tools you can run as part of
your build to give you more information
about your code quality that's something
that has received quite a bit of
attention over the last couple of years
yeah yeah this is this is something this
is probably that the next area which is
gonna see loads more tools coming in it
yeah and which is really great I mean
there's this you know your test code
coverage and and you know we even
getting project managers and program
managers come to us you know and say you
know I've got you know 40 projects under
my control I want to know how well
they're doing and one of the key metrics
that they're asking us for is I want to
see what the code coverage is across all
the team or all the programs you know
stuff like this you know bugs you know
leg analysis fine bugs as one of my
favorites for Java because it can can
pick up all these weird and wonderful
little issues that we get and again
style if you want to encourage
developers to work together you need to
kind of have some agreement within the
team on style and how are you going to
do it and so things like check style and
all the rest are great for enforcing you
know common readability rules throughout
your team again looking at cyclomatic
complexity
you know failing the build is that if
you get code that's too complex coming
in here you know failing the build if
your code coverage drops below a certain
percent yeah and stuff like this and
then also visualization being able to
visualize you know what the trains I'm
Mike oh you know where's it going
where's my performance going where's my
you know coverage going be able to see
all this and this is you know all the
metric stuff you know tracking you know
some of the the the issues around you
know performance code coverage build
times build times as a key one now
people like to start track you know as
my build suddenly gotten slower yeah you
know especially in functional tests
tests that are starting to interact with
the database if you build slows down all
of a sudden and you haven't really made
that many changes to your tests chances
are some you know that's an early stage
performance test you know flag that will
pop up and say hey there's something
wrong performance no code no no okay
let's look at testing tools so I guess
everybody knows that j-unit or whatever
unit and unit the unit as unit whatever
our unit so any other
things worth mentioning and will
probably work well we'll certainly have
an episode and test-driven development
attaching tools at some point but quick
overview yeah so testing the the unit
testing tools are now pretty well
understood and covered and stuff like
that but but there's something that
people are starting to talk about a lot
which is there's a whole group of them
collected together together Martin
Fowler calls and test doubles I'm not
sure if he coined the term or not but on
his blinky he's got a page about them
and that covers things like you know
stubs and mocking were you kind of
pretending to get information back or
you kind of you want to have a look at
the flow within one of your your classes
with on your objects seeing how they
have they're actually working I'm you
know and again things like behavior
driven development
and getting all this kind of information
in I'm you know running different types
of kind of business driven functional
tests you know foot tests selenium tests
you know driving the web browsers PR cow
on Monday we launched a new products
kind of that the first beta of a product
was called twist which is again about
you know having a whole IDE for managing
your your tests but having it in such a
way that even the management people who
kind of know what they want the system
can do can go in there and kind of
describe at a high level what they want
their code to do what they want the
application to do so there's lots of
kind of testing tools coming up here and
there's lots of interesting work going
on in or in in this area so again this
is probably one of the eight the other
ones that's that's kind of been there
from from the beginning but but it's
still got loads to get out loads of
value it's interesting to see that it's
probably it's fair to say that if we
want to increase or improve the state of
the practice and software development we
should focus more on those well not on
not on inventing yet another programming
languages rather on some of the in some
sense peripheral issues like build test
integration of the main experts and
stuff yeah exactly exactly it's you know
it doesn't matter how wonderful your
code is you know how clean and completes
and and and and and stuff your languages
but if you know if you can't test it if
you can't repeatably make sure that it's
doing what it needs to do for a business
to make money it's you know it's really
an academic exercise than anything else
yeah
finally I guess there is the the tools
that that you know pack all of this or
tag all of the stuff we talked about
together the the CI servers and of
course here doesn't mean corporate
identity but rather continues
integration yeah yeah and and again this
is somewhere where I've been quite
personally involved in in the past year
or two is is in watching how this the CI
servers have taken off you know it used
to be you know there was just cruise
control and then anthill came along and
then you know then there was some you
know bit of continuum and all the rest
and all these others and then all of a
sudden in the past two years there's
been this explosion there's you know
loads of different vendors out there
there's bamboo there's team city there's
you know Hudson this commercial ones
there's open source ones and that all
all trying different areas it's you can
see you know different people's approach
to continuous integration and what they
want to get out of continuous
integration and it's great seeing this
you know one of the the key trains that
emerging out of this is you know in the
old days you used to have a build server
and was a big build server and it used
to be a very expensive machine and you
know after a couple of years this thing
would would you know have if she's
coping with all your your projects you
know and you have real trouble getting
management buy-in to kind of upgrade the
the server because it used to be a
really heavy spec machine yeah nowadays
pretty much all the leading contenders
in the the CI server space all have this
concept of agents and yeah so you now
have not just one big server but you
have a build grid so they'll farm out
the jobs to whatever machines out there
yeah when I was you know trying our
product to to one of the big media
companies in the UK the guy Australia to
turn rack and said wow we now finally
have it have a use for all these over
powered machines we're putting on
management desktops you know connect
them agents in the background to be
running Bulls to be running unit tests
be running the code analysis built at
home right exactly having these big
grids and it's it's wonderful it's great
use of resources here and stuff like
this and also kind of helps particularly
for product companies it helps testing
on multiple platforms but right now what
you can do is you can have a stage
that's running tests on OSX on Linux on
you know windows and various flavors of
all of them and you know as long as all
the jobs you know running in parallel as
long as they all pass then the stage is
complete you know you've got
exactly the same bill that's passed on
all the platforms yeah and so I was
pulling all this you know a lot of them
are starting to put in personal builds I
I personally I'm not a huge fan of
personal builds I can see where they
have some value but personally I think
there's more value and kind of develop a
discipline in running local tests before
their check-in the whole concept is
instead of running your local tests on
your local machine to see can am i safe
to check my code in what you do is you
then basically say run a personal build
on the grid and what it'll do is it'll
take a diff of what's currently not
checked in on your machine submit it to
the CI grid and it will run in the full
CI environment and they give you a yes
or no and then you can say all right
okay it passed I'll check in or no it's
failed you know so on the flip side it
does have benefits that means you know
if if your build is a bit longer than
the normal check-in cycle you're still
testing in the right environment before
you check in and so kind of keeping less
impact on the rest of your team when you
make changes and stuff like this so
that's that's pretty common these days
pipelines there's one or two you know I
said our cruise product we the only ones
who really call it pipelines but you
know this there's similar things and
some of the the other products there's
this that they're following they don't
use the same names I can't remember the
names they used but pulse does something
similar
until produce something similar and you
know it's it's it's great I'm actually
I'm going straight from doubt to to kick
on the continuous integration testing
conference as well we you know this is a
time we're all ass guys kind of work on
these various products get to sit
together and get to talk about the
products and now and it's great because
we it's really driving out this
competition and we can start to see how
other people are thinking and
approaching this whole continuous
integration problem I guess that the
next level of granularity in tools above
the continuous integration server is
then stuff like for example jazz which
integrates version birth control but you
know reporting team collaboration change
sets environment replication and stuff
with testing building deploying so I
mean yes this this this whole team and
abling tooling yeah the whole
application lifestyle management
you know lifecycle management thing
which I'm very cold yeah it's exactly
bringing all these bits and pieces in
together and kind of bringing it all
into one space where you can kind of get
a general feel for how everything's yeah
and and and and and Express
relationships between things so that you
know that a certain commit of a certain
changeset resulted in you know this
isn't that subsequent problem yes if you
don't know that it's obviously hard to
trace things yes exactly and also
tracing further back up the try seeing
which stories which business
requirements actually drove those
changes in first place okay this brings
us to the end anything else any pearls
of wisdom as the space show guy likes to
say that you want to leave with our
listeners I'm probably the biggest thing
which I tell to all the clients where I
go and try and implement this always
they come to us and they say you know
can I have a CI health check can I see
what we're doing is is kind of be
pragmatic about it as it as in all
things these are these are guidelines
these are principles you've got to
choose the tools that fit most with your
way of working and enough and kind of
fit with the benefits that you want and
the pains are you having it kind of you
know it's it's not a silver bullet you
know I've been doing this for quite a
number of years now and it's it's not a
silver bullet as we said in the
beginning it's it's not something that's
totally isolated to the developers it's
got to expand your whole development
organization from the management right
all the way down to you to the Ops guys
looking after the production systems you
know unless everyone's kind of doing
their part and pulling their weight it's
it's it's really gonna be hard to put in
or hard to implement it's hard to look
after and hard to see the value mm-hmm
yeah yeah man I guess that's important
if you don't see the value people want
to be willing to do it exactly exactly
because it can't be a painful process
yeah okay then Chris thank you very much
for being on the show
great thanks for having me absolutely
[Music]
thanks for downloading and listening to
solve the engineering radio software
engineering radio is an educational
program brought to you by hillside
Europe if you want more information
about the podcast and all the other
episodes visit our website at st - radio
dot length if you want to support us you
can donate to the AC radio team via the
website or you can advertise for su
radio for example by clicking on the
dick reddit delicious and slash dog
buttons to contact the team please send
email to team at SC - radio net or if it
is specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under a
creative commons 2.5 license please see
the website for details thanks to
Charlie Crowell and the pod safe music
Network for the music used in the show
the song is called Vegas hard rock
travel
[Music]